Shri Krishna resides in our Vishuddhi Chakra.
Šrí Krišna sídlí v naší Višudhi èakøe.
In the center He resides as Shri Krishna.
V jejím støedu sídlí jako Šrí Krišna.
On the left-hand side His power, Vishnumaya, His sister, resides.
Nalevo sídlí jeho síla Višnumája, jeho sestra.
There He resides as Gopala,
Tam sídlí jako Gópala.
as the one who lived in Gokul played as a child.
Jako ten, kdo il v Gokulu a hrál si tam jako dítì.
On a right-hand side He resides
Na pravé stranì sídlí jako král,
These are the three sides of our Vishuddhi Chakra.
Toto jsou tøi strany Višudhi èakry.
The people who use their right side to dominate others,
Lidé, kteøí pouívají svou pravou stranu, aby ovládali ostatní,
use their voice to put down people,
pouívají svùj hlas, aby lidi poníili,
to show their authority,
aby ukázali svou autoritu,
shout at people,
aby na lidi køièeli,
are the people who get affected by the right side.
to jsou lidé, které postihuje tato pravá strana.
The right side is caught up
Pravá strana je blokovaná -
on the physical side you get a very big problem,
na fyzické úrovni získají velkı problém,
because the Right Heart cannot work out its flow.
protoe pravé srdce nemùe vypracovávat své proudìní.
So you get what you call asthma and all these diseases.
Pak dostanete astma a všechny tyto nemoci.
But specially when the Right Heart is affected
Zejména se to stává tehdy, kdy je pravé srdce postieno
by the fathers problem.
problémem s otcem.
On the left side is the Vishnumaya,
Na levé stranì je Višnumája
is the sisterly relationship.
- vztah se sestrou.
When the sister who is your pure relation
Kdy jednáte s vaší sestrou, která pøedstavuje èistotu vztahu,
is not treated as the sister,
jinak ne s vaší sestrou,
when the attitude of a person towards women
kdy je postoj èlovìka k enám
is of indulgence and of lust,
plnı ledabylosti nebo chtíèe,
then he develops the Left Vishuddhi.
pak dostane levou Višudhi.
When he develops a Left Vishuddhi very strongly
Kdy je jeho levá Višudhi pøíliš velká,
and if he has a bad Agya of he has eyes which are roving eyes,
kdy bude mít i špatnou Ádòu, která se projevuje jako toulavé oèi,
then this Left Vishuddhi causes lot of trouble.
tato levá Višudhi zpùsobí hodnì problémù.
Left Vishuddhi can be also caused by, as you know,
Levou Višuddhi mùe zpùsobit také,
by feeling guilty about things for nothing at all.
kdy se cítíte provinile kvùli èemukoliv.
All these problems arise from Vishuddhi.
Všechny tyto problémy pocházejí z Višudhi.
But Vishuddhi Chakra has a specialty.
Višudhi èakra ale má svoji zvláštnost.
When the humane beings raised their head upward
Kdy lidské bytosti pozvedly své hlavy
from Mother Earth towards the sky,
od Matky Zemì k obloze -
sky is, ether is Shri Krishna's nature,
obloha - etér je pøirozeností Šrí Krišny,
when it raises head towards the ether, towards the sky,
kdy èlovìk zvedne hlavu k etéru, k nebi,
then this Vishuddhi Chakra developed into a different dimension
pak se Višudhi èakra rozvine do jiné dimenze
and people started developing ego and superego.
a lidé si zaènou budovat ego a superego.
Superego was already developed,
Superego u bylo vybudováno,
but ego developed in such a way,
ale vybudovalo se natolik,
that it started suppressing the superego.
e zaèalo potlaèovat superego.
That's how you have got conditionings on one side
Takto získáváte na jedné stranì Višudhi podmínìnosti
of the Vishuddhi and ego on the other side.
a na druhé stranì ego.
When I told you the other day that you give up your free will
Kdy jsem vám jednou øíkala, e se zøeknete své svobodné vùle
in the sense that when you raised your head
v tom smyslu, e kdy jste pozvedli hlavu -
you did it through your free will with your power of growing,
udìlali jste to ze své svobodné vùle rùstu,
that you had as animals.
kterou jste mìli jako zvíøata.
After that now you have reached to the humane level.
Pak jste dosáhli lidské úrovnì.
And to rise above the humane level now
Jak vystoupit nad lidskou úroveò -
you have to do is to seek your complete freedom.
nyní musíte hledat svou úplnou svobodu.
And for that Vishuddhi Chakra is going to help you a lot.
K tomu vám hodnì pomùe Višudhi èakra.
On this Vishuddhi Chakra we have to really pay full attention.
Na této Višudhi èakøe musíte mít plnou pozornost.
It is such a complicated Chakra.
Je to komplikovaná èakra.
It has all the vowels of a Devanagari's script
Má všechny samohlásky devanagarského písma,
emitting out of the sound
které vydávají zvuky
of the shakti that is passing through it,
Šakti, kdy jí prochází
of the Kundalini that is passing through it.
Kundaliní.
So all the vowels are heard on these Chakras.
Take všechny tyto hlásky jsou slyšet na tìchto èakrách.
These vowels are, as you know, sixteen in number.
Tìchto samohlásek je 16.
Without the vowel
Bez samohlásek
in the Devanagari you cannot write anything.
nic v Devanagari nenapíšete.
Vowels are the sustenance,
Samohlásky tvoøí podporu.
are the power that
Jsou silou,
supports every consonant.
která podpírá kadou hlásku.
So it's very important that our vowels
Take je velice dùleité, aby naše samohlásky
have to be fully nourished and respected.
byly plnì vyivovány a respektovány.
The movement of the neck,
Pohyb krkem, jak jej dìlají lidé,
as you have seen in all international life,
jak jste na svìtì vidìli,
if you see, everybody has practically the same.
je prakticky stejnı u všech lidí.
Even those who cannot hear,
I ti, kteøí neslyší,
those who do not understand your language,
ti, kteøí nerozumí vašemu jazyku -
you can nod like this,
mùete hlavou kıvnout takto,
can say, "No", like this.
mùete øíct „ne“ takto.
Everyone understand this is "Yes" or "No".
Kadı rozumí, e toto je „ano“ a toto „ne.“
In some particular area
V nìjakıch oblastech
of course they have little different type of nodding.
máme samozøejmì rozdíly ve vıznamu kıvnutí.
But too much of nodding of head is not a very good sign.
Není ale dobré pøíliš hlavou kıvat.
I have seen people in the West,
Vidìla jsem, e lidé na Západì,
if you tell them something
kdy jim nìco øíkáte,
to show that they appreciated it,
tak aby vám ukázali, e to oceòují,
they'll go on for quite some time.
tak to budou dìlat docela dlouho.
That's not necessary.
To není potøeba.
Just have to say, "Alright", or "I've understood it", that's all.
Staèí øíct „jasnì,“ „chápu,“ to je vše.
You have to use your voice
Musíte pouívat svùj hlas místo toho, abyste poøád takto kıvali hlavou.
Is very bad, very-very bad for the Vishuddhi Chakra.
Je to velmi špatné pro vaši Višudhi.
Or some of them are the other way round.
Nìkteøí to dìlají naopak.
That whatever it is they'll put up their head like this
Cokoliv se dìje, dají hlavu takto
and they won't talk properly,
a nebudou otevøenì mluvit.
they will not say a word, they'll just keep quiet.
Neøeknou oni slovo, prostì budou zticha.
You may go on pinching them, doing anything, they won't badge.
Mùete je štípat, cokoliv, ale neuhnou.
This kind of personality is also very much detrimental
Taková osobnost je velmi škodlivá
to the growth of their evolution.
pro rùst jejich evoluce.
Apart from that, their Vishuddhi becomes a very big problem.
Kromì toho se jejich Višudhi stane velkım problémem.
Because of Vishuddhi there are so many problems.
Kvùli Višudhi existuje mnoho problémù.
Like angina you develop because of Vishuddhi.
Napøíklad anginu pectoris získáte skrze Višudhi.
You develop spondylosis because of Vishuddhi.
I spondylóza vzniká díky Višudhi.
Sometimes people lose their voices completely.
Nìkdy lidé úplnì pøijdou o hlas.
Sometimes they have all the time coughing.
Nebo lidé poøád kašlou.
And there are so many physical problems
Existuje mnoho tìlesnıch problémù
out of Vishuddhi because, as I said,
díky Višudhi, protoe, jak jsem vám øíkala,
this a very-very complicated center,
je to velmi sloité centrum.
which looks after your ear, nose, throat, all the sixteenth
Stará se o váš nos, uši, hrdlo, o všech 16
sub plexuses are there, which are looked after by this center.
podpletení se stará toto centrum.
But above all is the center of discrimination.
Nad tímto centrem je centrum rozlišování.
The center of discrimination only comes when you are free people.
Centrum rozlišování pøichází jen tehdy, pokud jste svobodní.
Till you are biased, till you have your own concept,
Dokud jste zaujatí a máte svoje pøedstavy,
you cannot be discrete.
nemùete mít rozlišování,
And that's the one point where one must understand
V tomto bodì musíte pochopit,
that to achieve your complete freedom,
e pokud máte získat úplnou svobodu,
you have to get your Vishuddhi Chakra cleared out.
musíte svou Višudhi úplnì vyèistit.
First and foremost thing is that we must speak in a sweet manner,
Pøedevší musíme mluvit líbeznì,
speak to someone in a sweet manner,
musíte s lidmi mluvit líbeznì,
not artificially, but sweetly.
ne afektovanì, ale líbeznì.
Speak in a manner that another person likes it.
Mluvte s lidmi tak, aby se jim to líbilo.
Saptyam vadeyt, priyam vadeyt.
Saptjam vadejt, prijam vadejt.
Speak the truth, don't tell the lies.
Mluvte pravdu, nelete.
If you go on telling lies after some time,
Pokud budete lhát, po nìjaké dobì
even if you tell the truth, it will become a lie.
i kdy øeknete pravdu, stane se z toho le.
But if you are telling the truth,
Pokud ale budete øíkat pravdu,
that even if you tell a lie, it becomes a truth.
pak i kdy øeknete le, bude z toho pravda.
Now some people
Nìkteøí lidé si myslí,
by their talks they can cheat people.
a e umí svımi slovy podvádìt ostatní,
But actually they are cheating themselves.
podvádìjí však sami sebe.
All such people who cheat others
Všichni ti, co podvádìjí ostatní
by sweet talks, by artificial talks
sladkımi a falešnımi øeèmi
or by some maneuvering
nebo nìjakım manévrováním,
go to such a horrible state
se dostanou do strašlivého stavu
and in this Kali Yuga specially they are cursed
a v této Kali juze jsou vıjimeènım zpùsobem prokleti,
and they get exposed and people know about them,
budou odhaleni a lidé o nich budou znát pravdu.
that these are the greatest liars ever known.
Budou vìdìt, e toto jsou ti nejvìtší lháøi na svìtì.
Now the times are coming
Nyní se blíí doba,
when all such people will be exposed
kdy všichni takoví lidé budou odhaleni
very much more than they have been ever exposed.
a to vıraznìji, ne kdy pøedtím.
So be careful not to think that you can cheat.
Buïte opatrní a nemyslete si, e podvádìt mùete.
In Sahaja Yoga specially you cannot cheat.
Zejména v Sahada józe nemùete podvádìt.
Those who try to cheat sometimes think that,
Ti, kteøí si myslí, e obèas podvádìt mùou:
"We can befool Mother, we can some or other carry on.
„Matku mùeme obelstít, nìjak to pùjde.
If we see in front of Mother She won't know, what we are up to".
Kdy se postaráme, aby to bylo pøed Matkou,
Is not so.
Tak to není.
I may not say, I may use My discretion not to say,
Moná to neøeknu, moná pouiju své rozlišování, abych nic neøekla,
I may allow you to have a long way, but be careful.
moná vám dovolím takto pokraèovat dlouho, ale buïte opatrní.
Do not come into My illusions,
Nedostaòte se do Mıch iluzí,
I'm very illusive.
jsem velice iluzorní.
And when I play My illusions you will suddenly find yourself
Kdy si budu se svımi iluzemi pohrávat, najednou zjistíte,
in a very difficult situation and then you will say,
e jste ve velmi sloité situaci, a pak øeknete:
"Mother, why am I in this situation?"
„Matko, proè jsem v této situaci?“
So this is one of the qualities of Shri Krishna
Take toto je jedna z kvalit Šrí Krišny.
that He is the one who becomes illusive.
On je ten, kterı se stává iluzorní.
And His illusiveness not cunning but illusive.
Jeho iluzornost není lstivá, ale šálivá.
In His illusiveness He exposes people to themselves.
Jeho iluzornost existuje, aby lidem odhalil jejich pravou tváø.
There are so many stories of Shri Krishna
Existuje mnoho pøíbìhù o Šrí Krišnovi,
in which He had illusively acted to give
ve kterıch zahrál iluzi o tom, e dává
greater joy to some people,
nìkterım lidem vìtší radost,
to give nice lessons to some people
aby jinım lidem udìlil pìkné lekce
and sometimes to punish.
a nìkdy aby potrestal.
For us it is important, that we are Sahaja Yogis,
Pro nás je dùleité, e jsme sahadajogíni,
in this lifetime we have a chance
e v tomto ivotì máme šanci na to,
our Kundalini has risen,
aby naše Kundaliní stoupala,
that we can face ourselves,
a e se mùeme sami sobì postavit èelem.
that we can correct our chakras,
Mùeme opravit své èakry,
that we know about ourselves,
mùeme poznat sami sebe,
that we know where is the problem is.
mùeme vìdìt, v èem je problém.
I've known of people who were caught up with left Vishuddhis
Poznala jsem lidi, kteøí mìli blok v levé Višudhi
and have become devilish by nature, devilish.
a stali se ïábelskımi, pøirozenì ïábelskımi.
They have gone out of Sahaja Yoga,
Odešli ze Sahada jógy.
they have criticized Sahaja Yoga,
Kritizovali Sahada jógu a snaili se Mi dìlat dost problémy.
So don't think that if Vishuddhi is spoiled
Nemyslete si, e kdy je Višudhi napadena,
there's nothing so special about it.
e to není nic mimoøádného.
It can be a very dangerous center.
Mùe to bıt velice nebezpeèné centrum.
Of course, Heart, Agya and Vishuddhi, these three centers
Samozøejmì, e srdce, Ádòa a Višudhi - tato tøi centra
one has to guard against
musíte ochraòovat,
because three of them can allow you
protoe tato tøi centra vám dovolí,
or can force you to become one with identification
nebo vás pøinutí, abyste se sjednotili a ztotonili
of evil as your own.
se zlem, jako byste to byli vy sami.
You might just feel that it's nice to be evil;
Mùete pak mít pocit, e je pøíjemné bıt ïábelskı,
you might just feel that it is a great fun to be evil
mùete mít pocit, e je to zábava bıt ïábelskı
and you might become evil.
a mùete se tak stát ïábelskım èlovìkem.
So at the Vishuddhi Chakra one has to be extremely careful.
Take u Višudhi èakry musíte bıt extrémnì opatrní.
Vishuddhi Chakra you looks after so many things,
Višudhi èakra se stará o hodnì vìcí,
specially your skin, your eyes.
zejména vaši kùi a o vaše oèi.
Skin is now I've seen people who have bad Vishuddhi
Vidìla jsem, e lidé, co mají špatnou Višudhi,
can have all kinds of funny troubles with their skins.
mají rùzné zvláštní problémy s kùí.
Of course, it has to do with your liver,
Samozøejmì e to souvisí s játry,
but skin is the way it shines,
ale zpùsob, jakım vaše ple záøí,
the way it glows,
zpùsob, jakım je prozáøená,
depends on how you smile,
závisí na tom, jak se usmíváte,
how you look at the world.
na tom, jak se díváte na svìt.
Many people have a habit of smiling for nothing at all.
Mnoho lidí má ve zvyku se usmívat bezdùvodnì.
Specially women I have seen, ladies I have seen,
Zejména jsem to vidìla u en.
they just smile stupidly.
Jen se hloupì usmívají.
That's not [inaudible], one should not be stupid.
To není ... nemìli byste bıt hloupí,
Stupidity is against Shri Krishna's principle.
Hloupost je proti principu Šrí Krišny.
Like you have seen the stupid people, how they are.
Vidìli jste hloupé lidi, jací jsou.
Their tongue is always halfway out.
Jazyk mají vdycky napùl venku.
If you have noticed the stupid man,
Všimnìte si, e kdy je nìkdo hloupı,
his face is that, his tongue is always out,
oblièej má takto, jazyk vdycky venku,
mouth half open and he looks like a dumbfound fool.
ústa napùl otevøená a vypadá jako naprostı hlupák.
Now in this only the Vishuddhi plays the part.
V tom hraje roli jen Višudhi.
Another one is the one where
Další vìcí je,
you get the Vishddhi's straits.
kdy získáte s Višudhi tíseò.
So such a person has very purse lips,
Takovı èlovìk má velmi našpulené rty,
angry lips and he doesn't talk.
naštvané rty a nemluví.
The another one might even get the expression of an idiot,
Další, co se mùe stát je, e máte na tváøi vıraz idiota.
but could be just making a face like that.
Nebo se tak bude jen tváøit,
Because if he's cunning he may take a
protoe je lstivı, mùe,
I would say a kind of a
øekla bych...
rupa or... (yogi: "Mask").
(øíká jogín) masku.
Mask you can say, a mask on his face,
Masku, dá si masku na oblièej,
that he is an idiot and make high to deceive you.
aby vypadal jako idiot a bude se snait vás takto oklamat.
So nothing is definite about Vishuddhi.
Take s Višudhi není nic definitivní.
Whatever may be the expression of a person,
Kadı vıraz v oblièeji èlovìka
a person may look very innocent.
mùe bıt vırazem nevinnosti,
Because that's the thing you can do with your Vishuddhi.
protoe to je to, co mùete s vaší Višudhi dìlat.
You are free because you've raised your head
Jste svobodní, protoe jste pozvedli své hlavy
and this point you have achieved, this kind of a special aptitude
a v tomto bodì jste získali mimoøádnou dovednost -
that you can deceive yourself and you can deceive others.
mùete sami sebe klamat a mùete klamat ostatní.
Some people look extremely innocent on the face.
Nìkteøí lidé mají nesmírnì nevinnı oblièej.
They may look to be very simple people,
Mohou vypadat jako velmi prostí lidé,
but may turn out to be horrid.
ale mùe se ukázat, e jsou ve skuteènosti strašliví.
Some people may look to be idiotic,
Nìkteøí lidé vypadají jako idioti,
but may be very intelligent.
ale ve skuteènosti jsou velmi inteligentní.
So it is how you play with your Vishuddhi
Je to podle toho, jak si hrajete se svou Višudhi,
which is, which is responsible.
která za to zodpovídá.
But the main thing what I'm trying to tell you,
To hlavní, co se vám snaím øíct, je to,
that you can maneuver your Vishuddhi.
e s Višudhi mùete manévrovat.
The way you want to put your expression,
Zpùsob, jakım chcete pouít svùj vıraz,
the way want you make your face,
jak se chcete tváøit,
the way you want to suggest something,
jak chcete nìco naznaèovat,
all you can maneuver
tím vším mùete manévrovat.
and you can keep your heart away from it.
Mùete své srdce nechat bokem.
In the heart you may have poison for a person,
V srdci moná pro nìkoho chováte jed,
but outwardly you may say
ale navenek mùete øíkat
to that person in a very sweet manner something
té osobnì nìco velmi líbeznì,
that a person might feel impressed.
abyste na toho èlovìka udìlali dojem.
But in this all this behavior, pattern of behavior,
Ale toto chování, celı tento vzorec chování,
you are deceiving yourself, not deceiving the another person.
znamená, e podvádíte sami sebe, ne toho druhého èlovìka,
Because yourself is Spirit,
protoe jste Duch,
which knows you very well.
kterı vás velmi dobøe zná.
And this will go on and on
Toto bude pokraèovat
for all your lives that have to come.
celé vaše ivoty, které budou následovat.
So there is no need in any way to be artificial in your expression,
Take není potøeba bıt jakkoliv ve svém vırazu afektovaní.
there is no need to hide anything in your expression.
Není potøeba nic z vašeho vırazu skrıvat.
Of course, I mean, if you don't like someone
Pokud se vám nìkdo nelíbí,
you need not just say, "I don't like you",
není potøeba øíkat „nelíbíš se mi,“
but in that case you have to be
ale v tomto pøípadì (ani) není nutné,
not also so much appreciative of the person,
abyste toho èlovìka pøíliš oceòovali.
that he's deluded into your appreciation.
Aby nebyl vaší chválou oklamán.
Now, eyes are very important
Oèi jsou velmi dùleité.
and eyes in a way are very much looked after by Vishuddhi
O oèi se z velké èásti stará Višudhi,
because the muscles of the eyes
protoe o vaše oèní svaly
are looked after by Vishuddhi.
se stará právì Višudhi.
And the kind of the muscles we have
Svaly, kterımi mùeme naše oèi vypoulit,
which close our eyelids and all that is very much suggestive.
které také zavírají naše oèní víèka, jsou velmi...
You must noticed that there are some people who come to Me,
urèitì jste si všimli, e jsou lidé, kteøí za Mnou pøijdou
their eyes go on like this.
a jejich oèi dìlají takto.
When they close their eyes, they cannot keep it shut.
Kdy své oèi zavøou, nemùou je mít dlouho zavøené.
There are some people, when they open their eyes to Me
Jsou lidé, kteøí kdy otevøou smìrem ke Mnì své oèi,
Both are in trouble.
Oba typy mají problém.
The ones which are the ones,
Ti, kteøí
are the people having supraconscious.
jsou ti, kteøí jsou v nadvìdomí.
And those who flicking their eyes are having the subconscious.
Ti, kteøí mrkají oèima, jsou v podvìdomí.
Some people have also
Nìkteøí lidé mají
habit of eh keeping the eyes in an angle all the time
zvyk se dívat v urèitém úhlu,
they never see you straight,
nikdy se na vás nedívají rovnì, ale dívají se úkosem.
Ah, they think it's sometimes it's very fashionable sometimes,
Myslí si, e je to nìkdy moderní,
ladies think it's a very good way of looking at people
eny si myslí, e je dobré se takto na lidi dívat,
and some of them have such eyes
nìkteré z nich mají takové oèi,
that they'll go on and looking and boring
budou se poøád takto dívat
their greedy eyes onto others,
na ostatní chtivıma oèima,
or their lusty eyes onto others.
budou ostatní chlípnì sledovat.
This is the worst thing you can do to your eyes,
Toto je to nejhorší, co mùete svım oèím udìlat,
because such people are easily can become blind.
takoví lidé mohou snadno oslepnout.
Such people might have trouble of the eyes.
Takoví lidé mohou mít problémy s oèima,
Specially reddening of the eyes
budou mít hlavnì zarudlé oèi.
can come to such people
To mívají takoví lidé velmi rychle.
So one has to be careful to keep the eyes very pure.
Take musíte bıt opatrní, abyste si své oèi udreli v èistotì.
The eyes of an Yogeshwara, who was Shri Krishna.
Oèi od Jógéšvary, kterı byl Šrí Krišna...
He was a witness,
Byl svìdek,
He, He was on this Earth,
byl na této Zemi,
He play, He played with Radha. He married five women,
hrál si s Radhou, oenil se s pìti enami,
they were the five elements.
bylo to pìt ivlù.
Sixteen thousand women He married,
Oenil se s 16 tisíci enami,
they were His sixteen thousand powers,
to bylo 16 tisíc jeho sil.
but He was Yogeshwara.
Ale On byl Jógéšvara.
He was Yogeshwara;
On byl Jógéšvara.
He had no lust in His eyes, in His mind about them, at all.
Ve svıch oèích k nim nemìl ádnı chtíè, vùbec.
He was beyond them, He was Yogeshwara.
Byl nad nimi, On byl Jógéšvara.
That was the testing point of His,
To byl jeho bod zkoušky,
that He had no lust in His eyes about these women that He had.
ve svıch oèích k tìmto enám nemìl ádnı chtíè.
Such an Yogeshwara is there!
Takovı Jógéšvara je tu!
Of course, I don't expect you to be Shri Krishna.
Samozøejmì neèekám, e vy budete Šrí Krišnou.
But you have your wife.
Máte svou enu.
Those who do not have wife must look forward to a wife.
Ti, kteøí nemají enu, se na ni musí tìšit.
That we'll get wives and will be,
Na to, e budeme mít kadı manelku...
ah, we'll have a wife and think of a wife,
e budete... myslete na manelku,
who will be your own
která bude vaší vlastní enou.
so that your eyes will not fall onto every woman
aby se vaše oèi nedívaly na kadou enu,
who comes across ah with that kind of a thing.
se kterou se potkáte.
I've seen people, even the photographs or anything they see,
Všimla jsem si, e i kdy vidí jen fotky
it's surprising, I mean, there's nothing in the photograph,
je to pøekvapivé - na fotce nic není, co je na fotce?
But even a photograph can attract their attention,
Ale dokonce i fotka mùe pøitáhnout jejich pozornost,
I mean, I don't know what can attract their attention like this.
nevím, co to je, co umí jejich pozornost tak pøitáhnout.
But they are so vulnerable and they have no control over their eyes.
Jsou tak zranitelní, nemají nad svıma oèima ádnou kontrolu.
No control, they become absolutely lost and they have no control.
ádnou kontrolu, zaènou bıt absolutnì ztracení a nemají ádné ovládání.
That shows that they have no powers in them
To ukazuje, e v sobì nemají ádné síly.
and they are slaves of their responses.
Jsou otroky svıch reakcí.
For the eyes are very-very important as Christ has said,
Jak øekl Kristus, oèi jsou velmi dùleité.
"Thou shalt not have adulterous eyes".
„Nebudete mít cizoloné oèi.“
There should be no adultery.
Nemìlo by tu bıt ádné cizoloství.
Some people have a habit of showing anger with the eyes, you see.
Nìkteøí lidé mají ve zvyku svùj hnìv vyjadøovat oèima.
If they have to show anger with their eyes
Kdy potøebují projevit zlost svıma oèima,
I need there not do that to you, but.
Tak se tady na vás nemusím dívat.
And the angry eyes you see are another dangerous things
Zlostné oèi jsou další nebezpeèná vìc,
to do with your eyes,
kterou mùete dìlat se svıma oèima,
because then they can become mesmeric.
protoe takové oèi umí hypnotizovat.
If you start putting your eyes onto something
Kdy zaènete nìco pozorovat,
First of all you'll catch bhoots in your eyes,
Nejdøív chytnete svıma oèima bhúty,
they'll settle down there and then
ti se tam usadí a pak
they will be falling on other people as bhoots.
budou na ostatní padat jako bhúti.
It's a very-very dangerous thing
Je to velmi nebezpeèná vìc,
to go on looking at something continuously with concentration.
dívat se na nìco s nepøe- tritım soustøedìním.
There's another kind of a stupid thing or a bhootish thing maybe,
Další hloupá nebo vìc plná bhútu je,
that people ask you to meditate here. It's absolutely wrong.
e vás lidé ádají, abyste tady meditovali. To je absolutnì špatnì.
In Gita it is written, still it is wrong.
Je to napsáno v Gítì, pøesto je to špatnì.
Nobody should put attention here.
Nikdo by tady nemìl dávat pozornost.
Instead of put attention, put attention at the door.
Místo toho dejte pozornost na dveøe.
What's the use of looking at a window?
Na co se dívat na okno?
You can't get out of it, can you?
Nemùete se z toho dostat, e?
If you have to look at anything be on a lookout for the door.
Kdy se na nìco musíte dívat, vyhlíejte dveøe.
And the door is here.
Dveøe jsou tu.
The door of Sahasrara is to be open out.
Dveøe Sahasráry je potøeba otevøít.
So you should not try to concentrate on this path.
Take byste se na tuto stezku nemìli soustøedit.
Many people who have concentrated on this path have become mad.
Mnoho lidí, kteøí se na tuto cestu soustøedili, se zbláznilo.
When they become mad, people say,
Kdy se nìkdo zblázní, lidé øíkají:
"These are Yogi but has got [SOUNDS LIKE - unmanitasha]."
„Jsou to jogíni, ale ...
That he moves like a madcap.
Pohybuje se jako blázen."
How can a Yogi be a madcap?
Jak mùe bıt jogín blázen?
That means he's united with God. Is He mad?
Znamená, e je sjednocen s Bohem, jak by mohl bıt blázen?
All such mad people are really mad,
Všichni takoví lidé jsou opravdu blázni,
they've nothing to do with God, definitely.
nemají s Bohem nic spoleèného.
But there are people who believe in such things,
Jsou ale lidé, kteøí takovım vìcem vìøí.
"Oh, he is in love with God,"
„Ó, on je zamilovanı do Boha,”
so he just jumps on the stage and goes into ecstasy,
take prostì v extázi skoèí na jevištì,
dances like a madcap.
a tancuje jako ztøeštìnec.
How can God be mad?
Jak by Bùh mohl bıt blázen?
First position is this that the sanest personality is God,
Nejvíc pøíèetná osobnost je Bùh, to je první pozice,
has to be.
tak to musí bıt.
From where do the sanity comes?
Odkud pochází pøíèetnost?
So this is one thing one has to understand,
Tuto jednu vìc èlovìk musí pochopit,
that any such practices
e byste nemìli dìlat jakékoliv praktiky, které vás mohou
Thirdly in the indiscretion that one has
Za tøetí - špatné rozlišování, které nìkdo má,
comes from people who are good hearted, nice people,
pøichází od dobrosrdeènıch, hezkıch lidí.
but they get kind away by the smiles of others
Nechávají se unést úsmìvy
or by the artificial goodness they show on their faces.
a falešnou dobrotivostí lidí, kteøí se pøetvaøují.
I've known some people, they always have a face like
Znala jsem lidi, kteøí mìli neustále na tváøi
as if they are all the time smiling.
(falešnı) úsmìv.
No, I can't do that way.
Ne, tak to nejde.
All the time if you look at someone like this, you see.
Vdycky, kdy se na nìkoho takového díváte..
It means as if you are mocking at the person.
Znamená to, e se tomu èlovìku vysmíváte.
And there are people I've seen who just like this
Vidìla jsem, e nìkteøí lidé
all the time have them [lips] like this.
mají poøád rty takto.
So, one should not be always in one pose.
Take èlovìk by nemìl mít stále jen jednu pózu.
Sometimes this muscles can get very weak
Nìkdy se tyto svaly velmi oslabí
and start paining if you take one.
a zaènou z toho bolet.
There are some others
Jsou lidé, kteøí se snaí poøád poukazovat na to,
I don't know what do they want to attract.
Nevím, co všechno dìlají, aby pøitáhli pozornost.
Attract the attention of others,
Aby pøitáhli pozornost ostatních,
attract ah the bhoots in themselves
pøitahují k sobì bhúty.
or I don't know what are they up to,
Nevím, co mají v plánu,
why can't they keep a normal face.
proè se nemohou tváøit normálnì.
Even while sitting in dhaan, or meditation,
Dokonce, i kdy sedí v meditaci,
I've seen that trying to show Me or may whatever it is,
vidìla jsem, e se to snaí Mì nebo ostatním ukázat,
because My eyes are mostly closed, but doesn't matter.
Moje oèi bıvají vìtšinou zavøené, ale to nevadí.
When I open My eyes I find some people like this, like that.
Kdy otevøu oèi, zjišuji, e nìkteøí lidé dìlají to a ono.
Why? What is the need? You have to have a balanced face.
Proè? Na co? Musíme se tváøit vyrovnanì.
That's what Shri Krishna had described the Sthita Pragya,
To popsal Šrí Krišna v Sthita Pragje.
One who is balanced,
Ten, kdo je vyrovnanı,
who doesn't laugh like an idiot,
se nesmìje jako idiot,
who laughs, but not like an idiot.
smìje se, ale ne jako idiot.
Nor he's a serious like another kind of an idiot.
Ani není vánı, jako bıvá jinı typ idiota.
So both the things are not at all
Take ani jedno, ani druhé
expression of your inner being.
nevyjadøuje vaši vnitøní bytost.
Such a person is, as I told you today,
Jak jsem vám dnes øíkala, takovı èlovìk není
is not frivolous, but not serious either,
ani lehkovánı, ani vánı,
but full of joy within himself.
jeho nitro je ale plné radosti.
He doesn't want you to be unhappy,
Nechce, abyste byli nešastní.
never would like that you should be unhappy people.
Nikdy by nechtìl, abyste byli nešastní.
But human beings if they want to be unhappy,
Pokud ale lidské bytosti chtìjí bıt nešastné,
what can anybody help,
co s tím mùe kdokoliv dìlat?
because they have got the free will to be unhappy.
(Nic), protoe máte svobodnou vùli bıt nešastní.
They have got a free will to cut their nose,
Mají svobodnou vùli si useknout nos,
they've a free will to cut their ears,
mají svobodnou vùli useknout si uši,
they've a free will to commit suicide.
mají svobodnou vùli spáchat sebevradu.
They have this free will so-called.
Mají takzvanou svobodnou vùli.
Now the greatest freewill comes from Vishuddhi Chakra,
Nejvìtší svobodná vùle pochází z Višudhi.
as I told you and that's why we call Him Yogeshwara,
Jak jsem vám øíkala, proto Mu øíkali Jógéšvara.
He is the Ishwara of Yoga.
On je Íšvara jógy.
The establishment of Yoga is possible
Ustanovení jógy je moné,
when you surrender yourself to Shri Krishna.
pokud se odevzdáte Šrí Krišnovi.
Completely surrenders yourself to Shri Krishna.
Odevzdejte se Šrí Krišnovi zcela.
Your Yoga will be established. Means what?
Vaše jóga bude ustanovena. Co to znamená?
Means all your balances will be established.
To znamená, e bude ustanovena kadá vaše rovnováha.
You go into complete balance
Dostanete se do úplné rovnováhy.
and that balance is complete because Vishnu,
Tato rovnováha je kompletní, protoe Višnu,
Who is the Incarnation for sustaining the dharma,
kterı jako inkarnace podporuje dharmu,
Who is responsible for giving you the balance,
kterı je zodpovìdnı za to, e vám dá rovnováhu,
becomes complete in the form of Shri Krishna.
se sám stane ve formì Šrí Krišny úplnı.
That's why He said that, "You leave all the dharmas
Proto øekl: „Všechny dharmy ponechejte (Mnì).”
[SOUNDS LIKE - sarva dharma nam partitte jam ma meik shana wraja]",
„Sarva dharma nam partitte jam ma meik shana wraja",
that's why surrender all of them to Me.
„proto je všechny ponechejte Mnì.”
So all the dharmas if you put it at the lotus feet of Shri Krishna,
Take kdy všechny dharmy odevzdáte u lotosovıch chodidel Šrí Krišny,
means if you follow His ideals,
to znamená, e pøijmete za své jeho ideály,
then all your dharmas are balanced.
pak budou všechny vaše dharmy uvedeny do rovnováhy.
But after Realization you go beyond dharma.
Vy ale po realizaci odboèíte z dharmy.
Whenever you go wrong in dharma,
Kdykoliv odboèíte z dharmy,
[SOUNDS LIKE - dharmatchutta] as they call it,
(dharma ???) ... se tomu øíká,
when you go wrong in dharma,
kdy vstoupíte do špatné dharmy,
that's the time you have to surrender yourself to Shri Krishna,
tehdy se musíte odevzdat Šrí Krišnovi,
so that He establishes your dharma.
aby vaši dharmu ustanovil.
There are so many dharmas.
Existuje mnoho dharem.
There is the pati dharm -
Existuje pati dharma,
husbands dharma, patni dharma - wive's dharma,
to je dharma manela, patni dharma - dharma manelky,
father's dharma, mother's dharma, son's dharmas,
dharma otce, matky, syna,
the [SOUNDS LIKE - rashtra] dharma - means the nations dharma.
... dharma národa.
Then you have all kinds of dharmas also
Pak existuje hodnì dharem ...
of we can say ah where one has to bow
mùeme øíci, klanìt se musíte
to the higher things of life.
v ivotì vyšším vìcem.
But then He says, "[SOUNDS LIKE - Sarva dharma anam pari tedg]"
On ale øíká „sarva dharma..,”
"Forget all the dharmas."
„zapomeòte na všechny dharmy.”
"[SOUNDS LIKE-Maa meikam charanam gachchhami ]", -
„má meikam èaranam gaèchámi,”
"Just surrender your dharmas, all of them to Me",
„jen své dharmy odevzdejte Mnì,”
that is at Vishuddhi.
tedy Višudhi.
At Vishuddhi Chakra you surrender all your other dharmas.
Ve Višudhi èakøe odevzdáváte všechny své ostatní dharmy.
It means that it all gets sublimated,
Znamená to, e vše zesublimuje,
it all gets complete, the wholesomeness is achieved
stane se úplnım, dosahujete celistvosti,
because He is collective being,
protoe On je kolektivní bytost.
He is the Virat,
On je Viráta,
because He is the integrated form of all the dharmas
protoe On je integrovanou formou všech dharem.
and He is the Virata in our brain.
On je Viráta v našem mozku.
He represents our brain.
On pøedstavuje náš mozek.
And when this Virat in us is awakened fully,
Kdy je tato Viráta plnì probuzena,
then all the dharmas become natural with us.
všechny dharmy se v našem nitru stanou naší pøirozeností.
We don't have to do any dharmas,
Nemusíme dìlat ádné dharmy.
we don't have to be conscious of any dharmas,
Nemusíme si bıt vìdomi ádné dharmy,
but automatically we become dharma ourselves.
automaticky se my sami staneme dharmou.
For example, there are people now, say, Christ;
Napøíklad, Kristus, øeknìme,
we can take example of Christ.
mùeme si vzít za pøíklad Krista.
He was dharma personified.
Byl zosobnìním dharmy.
He would not steal money from anybody, will He?
Nikomu by neukradl peníze, e?
Will He run away with somebody's wife, will He?
Neutekl by od své eny, e?
When He do anything wrong? No, He cannot.
Udìlal by nìco špatného? Ne, On nemùe.
Why? Because He was Dharma.
Proè? Protoe On byl dharmou.
So now you have become dharmateet,
Vy jste se nyní stali Dharmatít,
means you have entered into the kingdom of God,
to znamená, e jste vstoupili do Boího království,
into the Virata's conditions
do podmínek Viráty.
and there your condition is such that your state is such,
Tam je váš stav takovı, vaše podmínky takové,
your state is such, that you are dharma.
váš stav je takovı, e jste dharmou.
If you try to do adharma, you'll suffer.
Kdy se budete pokoušet konat adharmu, budete trpìt.
If you try to do wrong, you'll suffer.
Kdy se budete snait dìlat špatné vìci, budete trpìt.
Here I don't have to tell you to be righteous;
Tady u vám nemusím øíkat, abyste byli spravedliví,
I don't have to tell you, there's no need.
Nemusím vám to øíkat, není to potøeba.
I don't have to tell you that you tell the truth.
Nemusím vám øíkat, abyste mluvili pravdu.
I don't have to tell you, "Don't steal".
Nemusím vám øíkat, abyste nekradli.
I don't have to do all these things.
Nemusím vám øíkat všechny tyhle vìci.
Only thing I can tell you
Jedinou vìc vám mùu øíct:
that get rid of your ego and superego, that's all.
„Zbavte se vašeho ega a superga,” to je vše.
In a very general terminology.
Velmi všeobecnì øeèeno.
But you will follow Christ automatically,
Automaticky budete následovat Krista.
you will follow Krishna automatically, Sahaj,
Sahad, automaticky budete následovat Krista,
because now you have gone beyond dharma,
protoe nyní jste se dostali nad dharmu.
you have crossed the limits of dharma
Pøekroèili jste limity dharmy,
where you had to follow a dharma,
v nich jste museli následovat dharmu.
now you have become the dharma.
Nyní jste se stali dharmou.
Where you will stand, wherever you will be
A budete kdekoliv, kdykoliv,
dharma will stand with you.
bude s vámi stát dharma.
People will look at you and say, "Here is a dharma standing,
Lidé se na vás budou dívat a øíkat : „Tady stojí dharma.
he's the dharma to be worshipped".
On je dharmou, kterou je potøeba uctívat.”
Not because of anything but because your state
Není to kvùli nièemu, ale váš stav je
is that of dharma, you have gone beyond that.
stavem dharmy a vy jste se dostali nad ni.
Supposing this is loudspeaker I'm using today to talk to you.
Dnes s vámi mluvím pøes tento reproduktor,
But supposing this loudspeaker becomes part and parcel of Me,
kdy se ale, øeknìme, tento reproduktor stane Mou souèástí,
I don't have to use this, I go beyond it.
u to nemusím pouívat, nepotøebuji to.
In the same way
Stejnì tak vy nejdøíve pouíváte dharmu,
But when you go beyond dharma
Kdy se dostanete nad dharmu,
into the state of Virata,
do stavu Viráty,
then you don't need any dharma,
u nepotøebujete ádnou dharmu,
you become the dharma of Virat.
protoe jste se stali dharmou Viráty.
Now, what is the dharma of Virat,
Co je to dharma Viráty?
what is the dharma of Shri Krishna
Dharmou Šrí Krišny
is collectivity.
je kolektivita.
Krishna
Krišna
is the Brain.
je mozek.
Shiva is the Heart
Šiva je srdce.
and Brahmadeva is the Liver.
Brahmadéva jsou játra.
Now what's the faculty of this brain is?
Jaká je schopnost tohoto mozku?
That the tree of life of evolution grows downward as He says.
Øíká, e strom ivota a evoluce roste smìrem dolù.
And this tree is growing downwards
Tento strom roste dolù
of awareness from the brain.
ve vìdomí mozku.
But if you have to go to the roots
Pokud se máte dostat ke koøenùm,
you have to ascend and that ascent you have achieved,
musíte stoupat a tohoto vzestupu jste u dosáhli,
now you have gone to the roots of your brain
nyní jste šli ke koøenùm vašeho mozku,
where all your roots are enlightened,
tam jsou všechny vaše koøeny osvíceny,
all your nerves are enlightened,
všechny vaše nervy jsou osvíceny, váš mozek se osvítí
you are an enlightened person.
a vy se stanete osvícenım èlovìkem.
When you are in darkness
Kdy jste v temnotì,
you may catch hold of a snake as rope,
mùete chytnout do ruky hada a myslet si, e to je lano,
but when you are in light you will drop it.
kdy je tu svìtlo, tak ho hned pustíte.
In the same way, when you become enlightened,
Stejnì tak, kdy se stanete osvícenım,
your dharma is enlightened.
osvítí se vaše dharma.
You don't have to take to any guru
Nemusíte chodit za ádnım guruem,
or to any book or to anyone,
nemusíte èíst ádného knihy, nic,
you know yourself in your own life that this is wrong.
znáte sami sebe a víte, co ve vašem vlastním ivotì dìláte špatnì.
Now the collectivity part of it is very important.
Kolektivita je velmi dùleitá.
Anybody who cannot be collective is not yet a Sahaja Yogi.
Lidé, kteøí neumí bıt kolektivní, ještì nejsou sahadajogíni.
Not yet a Sahaja Yogi at all.
Ještì vùbec nejsou sahadajogíni.
Collective in the sense
Kolektivita v tom smyslu,
that anybody who cannot live with other Sahaja Yogis,
e kdo není schopen ít s dalšími sahadajogíny,
who tries to find faults with someone all the time,
ti, kteøí poøád na ostatních nacházejí chyby,
wants to run away with his wife
ti, kteøí se chtìjí dát na útìk s cizí manelkou
and'll stay somewhere else or with her husband,
a nìkde zaèít jinde, nebo s cizím manelem,
who wants to get out, is not a person who's collective.
ti, kteøí chtìjí bıt mimo, ti nejsou kolektivní.
There's no need to say
Není potøeba øíkat:
that, "I cannot live under the circumstances
„Za tìchto podmínek nemohu ít,
in which Sahaja Yogis can live".
jak ijí sahadajogíni, já nemohu ít.”
If you are a Sahaja Yogi, if are a Yogi, you can live.
Jestlie jste sahadajogín, jestlie jste jogín, tak takhle umíte ít.
Look at Me, I'm such an old woman, I can live anywhere.
Podívejte se na Mì, jsem u starší paní a umím ít kdekoliv.
You take Me to a village,
Vemte mì do vesnice - na jakékoli místo,
Because I'm comfortable within Myself.
Protoe mám pohodlí ve svém nitru.
My comforts are within.
Moje pohodlí je v Mém nitru.
In the same way, a person who is not collective,
Stejnì tak, èlovìk, kterı není kolektivní ...
like many people just come to Pujas, that's all.
hodnì lidí chodí jen na púde, to je vše.
It's like going to the church only once in Christmas
Je to jako kdy chodíte do kostela jen o vánocích
and then say, "Christ doesn't look after us".
a pak øeknete: „Kristus se o nás nepostaral.”
Of course, not going to church and you don't meet Christ,
Samozøejmì, nejde o to chodit do kostela a Krista taky nepotkáte,
but I mean to say that just to have a casual way
chci øíct, e ledabylım pøístupem
of Sahaja Yoga you cannot gain.
k Sahada józe moc nezískáte.
You have to be collective.
Musíte bıt kolektivní,
And collective means
kolektivní znamená,
that at every collective program you should be there.
e musíte bıt na kadém kolektivním programu.
You should always meet collectively,
Vdycky byste se mìli kolektivnì scházet,
meditate collectively, live collectively,
kolektivnì meditovat, kolektivnì ít
and try to find ways and methods of being collective.
a snait se najít zpùsoby a metody jak bıt kolektivní.
There are so many evil forces,
Existuje mnoho ïábelskıch sil,
which are all the time trying to attack collectivity.
které se neustále snaí na kolektivitu zaútoèit.
First they will attack the leaders.
Zaènou útokem na lídry. To je první vìc.
Any leader tell somebody, "You shouldn't do like this",
Kdy nìjakı lídr øekne: „Toto bys nemìl dìlat,”
immediately that person will start spreading stories against,
ten èlovìk okamitì zaène šíøit pøíbìhy proti lídrovi.
"That leader is very bad, he's like this, he's very harsh.
„Ten lídr je velmi špatnı, je takovı, je moc pøísnı.
He didn't garland me, he didn't give me this, that".
Nedal mi oslavnı vìnec, nedal mi to a ono.”
How can you garland a bhoot, can you?
Jak mùete oslavovat bhúta? To nejde.
That if that in that ah doesn't work out
Kdy se to takto nevypracuje,
then they have their sly methods
mají své vlastní lstivé metody,
of going round and talking something here and there
chodí a vyprávìjí lidem do uší (rùzné vìci),
in the ears to create some sort of a politics.
aby vytvoøili nìco jako politickou (kampaò).
All such people will be thrown out of Sahaja Yoga.
Všichni takoví budou ze Sahada jógy vyhozeni.
As there is a centrifugal and a centripetal force,
Existuje tu odstøedivá a dostøedivá síla,
both acting equal and opposite.
která koná rovnocennì i v protikladu.
Anybody who goes against collectivity,
Všichni, kdo jdou proti kolektivitì,
who sticks to their bhoots, sticks to their negativity
kteøí se drí svıch bhútù, drí se své negativity,
will have to get out of Sahaja Yoga
pùjdou se Sahada jógy pryè.
and that's is to be remembered,
To si musíte pamatovat,
that to be collective is to be joyous,
e kolektiv má bıt radostnı,
is to be progressive, to be going further.
má bıt pokrokovı a má postupovat.
It was alright when people were meditating in the Himalayas.
Bylo to v pohodì meditovat si v Himalájích,
It was alright at that time they were all alone,
fungovalo to, kdy tam byli sami,
meditating all alone,
meditovali si sami,
to achieve something for the collective.
aby nìco pro kolektiv dosáhli.
But they also did not get their Realization.
Ale ani tak nezískali svou realizaci.
When you have got your Realization remember this.
Kdy u máte svou realizaci, pamatujte na to,
Now you have entered into the Kingdom of God,
e nyní jste vstoupili do Boího království,
into the Kingdom of Virat
do království Viráty,
where you are a part and parcel of a collective being.
kde jste nedílnou souèástí kolektivní bytosti.
You are not alone, you cannot be single out,
Nejste sami, nemùete bıt oddìleni,
you cannot separate yourself.
nemùete se osamostatnit.
Now you are awakened in the body of Virata
Nyní jste probuzeni v tìle Viráty,
and you cannot get out of it.
nemùete se dostat pryè.
If you try to get out of it, you cannot be nourished.
Kdy se budete snait oddìlit, nemùete dostávat vıivu.
Supposing, I take out part of My body.
Napøíklad vás vyjmu ze svého tìla.
Will it be nourished by this body? It won't.
Bude vás toto tìlo nadále vyivovat? Nebude.
In the same way you have now become
Nyní jste se stejnım zpùsobem stali
part and parcel of that collectivity
nedílnou souèástí kolektivity
and that collectivity that Virat is going to look after you,
a tato kolektivita, která je Virátou, se o vás bude starat,
going to nourish you,
bude vás vyivovat,
going to do the everything that is necessary
bude dìlat vše, co je potøeba
for your spiritual, physical, mental, emotional,
pro váš duchovní, tìlesnı, mentální a citovı,
even financial development.
dokonce i finanèní rozvoj.
But if you cut it short, if you
Kdy se ale odøíznete,
try to block the collectivity,
kdy se budete snait blokovat kolektivitu,
if you try to make problems for collectivity
kolektivitì dìlat problémy,
or even if you try just to get out of the collectivity,
i kdy se budete snait jen z kolektivity dostat pryè,
then that is not our interest, that is not our work.
pak to není to v našem zájmu, pak to není naše práce.
This is to be understood fully,
Toto je potøeba plnì pochopit
in every way possible
v kadém moném smìru,
and this when is understood in a proper way,
a kdy je to øádnì pochopeno -
you should know that
mìli byste vìdìt,
collectivity is not only your advancement,
e kolektivita není jen pro váš pokrok,
is not only your development,
nejen pro váš vıvoj,
is not only your achievements,
nejen pro vaše úspìchy,
is the achievement of the whole humanity.
je to pro úspìch celého lidstva.
The purpose of your creation
Úèel vašeho stvoøení tak
is fulfilled by that.
bude naplnìn.
Those people who live in the ashram
Lidé, kteøí ijí v ašrámech
are better of always, than the people who live alone, always.
jsou na tom vdy lépe, ne ti, co ijí sami.
They will always have better results,
Vdycky budou mít lepší vısledky
than the people who live alone.
ne lidé, kteøí ijí sami.
Maybe they live alone
Moná ijí sami, protoe chtìjí mít trochu soukromého ivota,
That's not going to help them at all.
To jim vùbec nepomùe.
The more we live together,
Èím více spolu ijeme,
the more you reside together,
èím více spolu sídlíte,
the more you enjoy together,
èím více se spolu radujete,
there will be greater chances of your advancement.
tím vìtší jsou vaše šance na váš vzestup.
The more you will try to make yourself private,
Èím více se budete snait mít pro sebe soukromí,
the more you'll try to get out of it,
èím více se budete snait bıt bokem,
whatever explanation you may give,
a pro to budete mít jakékoliv vysvìtlení,
God understands, very well.
Bùh tomu všemu velmi dobøe rozumí.
So all such things where you cut off yourself
Všechny ty vìci, kterımi se vzdalujete
from the mainstream,
z hlavního proudu -
you try to get out of the main stream,
kdy se snaíte dostat z hlavního proudu,
then there is a big problem for you.
pak je ve vašem nitru velkı problém.
Of course, for certain conveniences you may,
Samozøejmì, e kvùli jisté vhodnosti mùete...
for your certain understanding you may,
z nìjakého porozumìní mùete...
but you should enjoy more the company of Sahaja Yogis,
mìli byste si ale více uívat, kdy jste se sahadajogíny,
than your own private company
ne kdy jste sami,
in the dingy room of yours.
ne kdy jste v té vaší neutìšené komnatì.
That is one thing you can judge yourself.
V tomto mùete sami sebe soudit.
Do you all enjoy the company of Sahaja Yogis
Uíváte si spoleènost sahadajogínù,
or you enjoy the company
nebo si uíváte (víc) spoleènosti
Judgment is your own.
To posuïte sami.
Yogi "A difficulty Shri Mataji".
Jogín: „Problém, Šrí Mátadí.”
Nothing is difficult in Sahaja Yoga.
V Sahada józe není nic obtíné.
It is the simplest thing to be a Sahaja Yogi.
Je to ta nejjednodušší vìc bıt sahadajogínem.
And even more simple to be collective.
Ještì jednodušší je bıt kolektivní.
To be uncollective you have to do something.
Abyste byli nekolektivní, musíte nìco udìlat.
Like I said that it is very easy not to drink.
Je velice snadné nepít, jak jsem vám øíkala.
Mean, I mean, drink some wines and things.
Myslím tím pít víno a podobnì.
Because if you don't want to drink you are sitting at home,
Pokud nechcete pít, sedíte doma,
it's alright, don't have to do anything.
je to v poøádku, nic nemusíte dìlat.
But supposing you have to drink,
Ale kdy musíte pít, musíte jít do hospody nebo za nìkım,
open the bottle, get a particular type of a glass,
musíte si otevøít láhev, sehnat si konkrétní typ sklenièky,
pour it down, this, that.
nalít to, spoustu vìcí musíte udìlat.
In India, for example, where there is prohibition,
Napøíklad v Indii, kde máme prohibici,
you are sitting with a fright.
sedíte se strachem.
But for a person who just drinks water he doesn't have to do it.
Èlovìk, kterı pije vodu, to dìlat nemusí.
So to do wrong one has to do something.
Abyste mohli udìlat nìco špatného, musíte nìco udìlat.
But to be good you don't have to do much.
Abyste byli dobøí, nemusíte toho moc udìlat.
Is absolutely labor saving, energy saving process
Úplnì to šetøí práci, je to proces, kterı šetøí energii.
You see, to do bad, supposing, you see,
Abyste dìlali špatné vìci - napøíklad,
I ah want to harm somebody,
chcete nìkomu uškodit,
I'll have to go out of the way to find out ways, methods.
tak musím jít a vymyslet nìjaké zpùsoby a metody.
If I to tell lies I have to think of ten lies to cover that one lie.
Kdy chci lhát, musím si tìch lí vymyslet deset a pak jednu skrıvat.
But if I tell the truth, finished,
Kdy ale øíkám pravdu, hotovo,
So to be collective is much more easier.
Bıt kolektivní je také mnohem jednodušší.
Of course, not for crooked people,
Není to tak pro køiváky,
because crooked people whenever they move
protoe køiví lidé, kamkoliv jdou,
their angularities trouble others.
tak svojí hranatostí otravují ostatní.
You see, like ah ah poking ah of thorns.
Zraòují svımi trny.
But those who are flowers they fitting anywhere,
Ti, kteøí jsou jako kvìtiny, ti se hodí všude,
people like them.
lidé je mají rádi.
They like their fragrance,
Milují jejich vùni.
they look at them, they enjoy them beautiful things.
Dívají se na nì a radují se z tìch krásnıch (lidí).
Now see, today they are looking like lotuses.
Podívejte se, dnes vypadají jako lotosy.
How is it? Without doing anything they have become lotuses.
Jak je to moné? Ani by cokoliv udìlaly, staly se lotosy.
How? How they have become like lotuses?
Jak se z nich staly lotosy?
Whether they are lotuses or they are daisies God only knows.
Jestli to jsou lotosy nebo kopretiny, to ví jen Bùh.
But they have become lotuses Sahaj.
Staly se ale lotosy sahad zpùsobem.
How? Because they are one with God.
Jak to? Protoe jsou sjednocení s Bohem.
When we stand in our own way,
Kdy se snaíme stát po svém, osamocenì,
when we try to do something privately,
kdy se snaíme nìco dìlat soukromì,
then God said, "Alright, go private'.
pak Bùh øekne: „Dobøe, mìj své soukromí.”
But when we are public He looks after us.
Kdy jsme kolektivní, pak se o nás stará.
And then in Sahaj Yoga, as you know,
Jak víte, v Sahada józe
that collective growth
je kolektivní rùst
is the only way we understand Sahaj Yoga.
jedinım zpùsobem, jak pochopit Sahada jógu.
Somebody knows something, somebody knows something else,
Nìkdo nìco ví, nìkdo zná nìco jiného,
somebody knows something else.
nìkdo zná zase nìco jiného.
When we are collective,
Kdy jsme kolektivní,
Supposing, there is somebody a scientist,
Napøíklad, nìkdo je vìdec,
somebody is a musician,
nìkdo je hudebník,
somebody is another thing.
nìkdo má další povolání.
We cannot know everything.
Nemùeme znát vše.
So you know something from this one,
Take nìco znáte od jednoho èlovìka,
something from that one,
od dalšího nìco jiného, a nìco zase od dalšího.
So all the rivers has it's flowing into that collectivity
Take všechny øeky teèou do stejné kolektivity
and you enjoy the ocean of these ah rivers.
a vy se radujete z tohoto oceánu všech øek.
You don't have to go to all the rivers in India,
Take nemusíte jít ke všem øekám v Indii,
like you go from Ganga, Yamuna, Saraswati, Kaweri
jako k Ganze, Jamunì, Sarasvatí a Kaveri,
you thousands of lives.
(je to jako) tisíc ivotù. Jdìte k moøi, všechny jsou tam.
Like that you have to enjoy the sea where everything meets.
Takto se budete muset radovat z moøe, kde se setkává vše.
All kinds of beautiful things are there and you enjoy that.
Jsou tu všechny krásné vìci a vy se z nich radujete.
I hope this Puja which is a very remarkable Puja.
Doufám, e tato púda... je to velmi pozoruhodná púda.
Firstly so many things are Sahaj.
Za prvé, tolik vìcí je sahad.
Firstly they told Me
Nejdøíve Mi øíkali,
the telephone number of this place is 32 16 32.
e telefonní èíslo sem je 32 16 32.
He, He's accompanied by 64 Yoginis, Shri Krishna.
On je doprovázen 64 jogínkami - Šrí Krišna.
So 32 on this side and 32 on that side and He sitting here
Take 32 na kadé stranì a On sedí zde.
This place is called as Black ah Lake.
Tomuto místu se øíká Èerné jezero.
Krishna is black.
Krišna je èernı.
This place they got suddenly
Tohle místo získali znenadání
and this is the only place in this
a  je to jediné místo
so-called military regime of Switzerland
v tomto takzvaném vojenském reimu Švıcarska,
where people can sleep on the ground.
kde lidé mohou spát na zemi.
You are not supposed to sleep on the ground.
Nepøedpokládáte spát na zemi.
If there's no cot you hang in the
Kdy tu není postel, zavìsíte se
air, but you cannot touch the ground.
do vzduchu, ale nemùete se dotıkat zemì.
That kind of the stupid military business is here.
Je tady takovı stupidní vojenskı styl.
Where to find such a sensible, practical,
Kde najít rozumné, praktické (místo)
such a cheap place for you is godsent.
- toto levné místo je dar z nebes.
We are here surrounded by beautiful things with the cows,
Jsme tu obklopení krásnımi vìcmi, jsou tu krávy,
so many cows at the time when it is Krishna's birthday.
tolik krav v den narozenin Šrí Krišny.
So many cows, so fond of cows
Tolik krav, mìl krávy moc rád,
and the cows when they their bells
kdy kravám na krku ráno
move in the morning I heard, in the evening so beautiful
cinkají zvonky - veèer je to tak krásné,
and when they are moving home in the evening
veèer se vracejí domù,
how the as they call [SOUNDS LIKE -guraj] -
jak se øíká ...
is the dust of their feet was filling the sky
prach z jejich kopyt naplòuje oblohu,
is just Gokul here I felt.
cítila jsem se jako v Gókulu.
Today also there's one thing more one has to say,
Dnes musím øíct ještì jednu vìc,
that is the sixteenth Shri Krishna Puja.
dnes je to šestnáctá púda ke Šrí Krišnovi.
So in so many ways this is a very great Puja
Take v nìkolika smìrech je to skvìlá púda,
which you are attending for which
které se úèastníte,
people have to take thousands and thousands of janmas (births)
a na kterou èlovìk èeká tisíce a tisíce zrození.
do so many punyas, which you have got so Sahaj,
Musí vykonat nìkolik punjas, které jste získali tak sahad,
because there must be something about you people also.
protoe na vás je (také) nìco mimoøádného.
May God bless you.
Nech vám Bùh ehná.